Inventory of the Stanisław Ciosek papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Stanisław Ciosek papers
1940-2014
1980-1989
2017C44
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes (2.7 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoirs, other writings, notes, memoranda and reports relating to negotiations for transition of Poland from a communist to a non-communist regime, and to Polish relations with the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Ciosek, Stanisław, 1939-
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2017.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collection(s)
Krzysztof Dubiński: Okrągły Stół collection, Hoover Institution Archives Mieczysław F. Rakowski papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Stanisław Ciosek was born in 1939 in a village in central Poland, where both of his parents were school teachers with progressive leanings. At twenty he joined the communist Polish United Workers Party, and two years later completed a degree in economics. His first party work assignment was in the Polish Students’ Association, the only government-sanctioned organization for academic youth. He led that organization until the age of thirty-six, when the party found another position for him: the chairmanship of the party and provincial regional government of Jelenia Góra, in the southwestern corner of the country near the Czech and East German borders. Ciosek did well in his assignment and in 1980 was promoted to membership in the Central Committee of the party and transferred to Warsaw.
Ciosek’s new specialty was labor and unions, which in Poland of the 1980s meant counteracting the growth of the Solidarity trade union. He served as minister of labor from 1983 to 1984. Ciosek was made a full member of the Politburo of the party in 1988 and took part in negotiations with the Solidarity opposition in a series of meetings in Zawrat and Magdalenka, paving the way for the "round table" talks between the Communists and Solidarity opposition in the early months of 1989. These talks, in which Ciosek played a prominent part, made the semi-free elections of June 1989 possible. He ran for a seat in the Parliament during these elections but lost, as did all of the party candidates, some of whom blamed Ciosek for the disaster.
At the end of 1989 the newly elected Polish president, Lech Wałęsa, along with the new premier, Tadeusz Mazowiecki, tapped Ciosek to be Poland’s ambassador in Moscow; he accepted. After returning to Poland in 1996, he became an adviser on Russia and the post-Soviet countries to President Aleksander Kwaśniewski.
Scope and Content of Collection
Stanisław Ciosek’s papers and photographs document mostly the years 1980 to 1996: his tenure as minister of labor, as well as a Central Committee and Politburo member, endeavoring to contain the rise of the Solidarity trade union movement, followed by nearly seven years of work as the new Poland’s ambassador to Moscow.
Ciosek's Moscow papers include copies of important documents mixed with cryptic scribbles and doodles. His memoirs, Wspomnienia (niekoniecznie dyplomatyczne): opowiastki z Polski i Rosji (Memoirs (Not Necessarily Diplomatic): Tales from Poland and Russia), published in 2014, provide something of a guide to his papers. Of much interest in the collection are Ciosek’s efforts to arrange for an orderly evacuation of Soviet/Russian troops from Poland, and his meetings with Gorbachev, Yeltsin, and the young Vladimir Putin (still under the wing of Anatoly Sobchak, the mayor of St. Petersburg). Also of interest is Ciosek’s relationship with Gennady Yanayev, Gorbachev’s vice president, and leader of the failed August 1991 coup. Ciosek’s ambassadorial papers are a significant source on recent Polish diplomacy and on Russia’s "time of troubles" in the 1990s.
Poland--Politics and government--1980-1989.; Labor movement--Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--Russia (Federation); Russia (Federation)--Foreign relations--Poland.
- Odręczne notatki z prac rządowych, 1980-1988 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Super tekst Nr. 1, 1987 January 10 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Propozycje posunięć na rok 1987 z udziałem generała Pożogi i J. Urbana.
- Super tekst Nr. 2, 1987 April (Box-folder 1: 3)
  Projekt doskonalenia polityczno-gospodarczego wstrząsu - NOPEG (Nowa Polityka Gospodarcza).
- Raporty S. Cioska do J. Jaruzelskiego (MSW), 1987 September 3 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Raporty S. Cioska do J. Jaruzelskiego (MSW), 1988 January 28 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Raporty S. Cioska do J. Jaruzelskiego (MSW), 1988 August 11 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Pismo do gen. W. Jaruzelskiego, 1987 May 18 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  Z prośbą o poszerzenie składu Rady Konsultacyjnej oraz propozycja dla L.Wałęsy.
- Pisma do gen. W. Jaruzelskiego, 1987 May 29 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  Związane z inicjatywą L. Wałęsy.
- Zapiski z nasłuchu RWE oraz z rozmów z przedstawicielami Episkopatu, 1987 December 30 (Box-folder 2: 3)
- Synteza sytuacji wewnętrznej kraju i działań Zachodu, 1987 August 28 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Kierunki reformy systemu politycznego w Polsce, 1988 August 10 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  Zarys propozycji.
- Reforma systemy politycznego - w kierunku pluralizmu i pogłębienia demokracji, 1988 August 30 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Analiza dokonana przez MSW - nastroje społeczne, 1988 January 28 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  Dokument z poprawkami skierowany do J. Urbana.
- Scenariusz przełomu i scenariusze niepowodzenia, 1988 March 18 (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Pismo do gen. W. Jaruzelskiego, 1988 December 18 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  Propozycje na Plenum, ideogram.
- Odręczne notatki ze spotkań, 1987 January 29 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  Między innymi w Klarysewie; B. Geremek.
- Aneks do prognozy na rok 1988, 1988 January 19 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  A. Gdula do S. Cioska.
- Informacje z Komitetu Centralnego PZPR o sytuacji w kraju, 1988 May (Box-folder 3: 1)
- Notatki z rozmów, 1981-1988 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  Między innymi z ks. Orszulikiem oraz W. Siłą-Nowickim.
- Materiały dotyczące rozmów rząd - Kościół, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  Notatka ze spotkania Rakowskiego z władzami Kościoła. Materiał roboczy dotyczący Okrągłego Stołu.
- Związki zawodowe, 1982 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  Dyskusje nad ustawami i formą.
- Varia, 1986 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  Wspomnienia Rakowskiego z pobytu w Korei Północnej, tekst wręczony przez Siłę-Nowickiego, notatka między Cioskiem i Urbanem.
- Rozmowy z Lechem Wałęsą, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- Rozmowy z przedstawicielami Kościoła, 1989 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  Macharski, Stroba, Orszulik oraz Tadeuszem Mazowieckim.
- Założenia ideowo-programowe i kierunki polityki społeczno-gospodarczej NSZZ "Solidarność,", 1981 April 14 (Box-folder 3: 8)
- Program NSZZ "Solidarność" uchwalony przez I Krajowy Zjazd Delegatów, 1981 October 16 (Box-folder 3: 9)
- Materiały pomocnicze do rozmów z opozycją, 1981-1988 (Box-folder 3: 10)
- M. Rakowski, 1987 June 8 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  Uwagi dotyczące niektórych aspektów politycznych i gospodarczych. Sytuacji PRL w II połowie lat osiemdziesiątych.
- Notatka dla gen. W. Jaruzelskiego, 1986 October 18 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  Dotyczące spotkania w Belwederze.
- Notatka w sprawie porozumień społecznych, 1985 July (Box-folder 3: 13)
- Zapiski ze spotkania Cz. Kiszczaka z L. Wałęsą, 1988 August 31 (Box-folder 3: 14)
- Zapiski z rozmów z Episkopatem ("a modo privado"), 1988 April (Box-folder 3: 15)
- Notatki z rozmów o "Solidarności,", 1981 December (Box-folder 4: 1)
- Notatki z rozmów z kierownictwem "Solidarności,", 1981 February-March (Box-folder 4: 2)
- Notatka służbowa ze spotkania roboczego w URM, 1980 December (Box-folder 4: 3)
  Ustalenia zawarte w Stoczni Gdańskiej, 31 sierpnia 1980.
- Komunikaty z badań OBOP, 1982 (Box-folder 4: 4)
- Notatka dla W. Jaruzelskiego, 1982 June (Box-folder 4: 5)
  W sprawie organizacyjnych rozwiazań przyszłości ruchu związkowego.
- Odręczne notatki S. Cioska, 1980 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  Dotyczące VII Plenum KC oraz realizacji porozumień sierpniowych.
- W. Bieńkowski, Zrozumieć społeczeństwo, 1988 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  Maszynopis książki.
- Materiały dotyczące Lecha Wałęsy, 1983 (Box-folder 4: 8)
- Zespół ds. Związków zawodowych (Box-folder 4: 9)
  Materiały odręczne i notatki.
- Materiały dotyczące ugody: rząd-opozycja, 1982 (Box-folder 4: 10)
- Narada I sekretarzy Komitetu Wojewódzkiego, 1982 October 14 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  Notatki odręczne.
- Okrągły Stół, notatki, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 12)
- Propozycje programowo-organizacyjne Rady Politycznej, 1989 (Box-folder 5: 1)
- Okrągły Stół, 1989 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  Notatki odręczne i maszynopisy.
- Negocjacje z opozycją, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  Notatki odręczne i maszynopisy, pisma i listy.
- Dialog społeczny; listy, notatki odręczne, pisma, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 5: 4)
- Nowa polityka wschodnia, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 5: 5)
- Raport polityczny Ambasady RP w Moskwie, 1989 (Box-folder 5: 6)
- Sejmowe exposé Ministra Spraw Zagranicznych RP K. Skubiszewskiego, 1990 April 26 (Box-folder 5: 7)
- Wizyta oficjalna Prezydenta Federacji Rosyjskiej Borysa Jelcyna w RP, 1993 August 24-26 (Box-folder 5: 8)
- Stosunki gospodarcze pomiędzy Polską a Federacją Rosyjską, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 6: 1)
- Wizyta ministra MSZ K. Skubiszewskiego, 1990 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  Zapisy rozmów i notatki odręczne.
- Wizyta T. Mazowieckiego w Moskwie, 1989 November 23-24 (Box-folder 6: 3)
- Wizyta L. Wałęsy w Moskwie, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  Materiały do wizyty L. Wałęsy w Rosji.
- Korespondencja dyplomatyczna, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 6: 5)
- Zdjęcia (tzw. oficjalne) ze spotkań dyplomatycznych, posiedzeń partyjnych i wizyt, 1970-1990 (Box-folder 7: 1)
- Zdjęcia prywatne S. Cioska, 1940-1970 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  Wczesne dzieciństwo i młodość.
- Wspomnienia (niekoniecznie dyplomatyczne): opowiastki z Polski i Rosji, 2014 (Box-folder 7: 3)